<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>MAE 297 - Jason K. Moore, PhD</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/</link><description>Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering Seminar</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Plasma Based Surface Hardening of Metals</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/petros-abraha.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Surface hardening is a process that includes a wide variety of techniques used
to improve the wear resistance of metallic parts without affecting the softer,
tough interior bulk material. Hardened metals are usually more brittle than
softer metals, there fore, hardening metals throughout the surface and bulk, is
not always a suitable choice of treatment for parts subject to various kinds of
stresses. In such circumstances, case-hardening can provide a better solution
against fracture and adequate wear resistance. There are several methods of
surface hardening techniques: flame hardening and induction heating; and
diffusion methods such as carburizing and nitriding. The …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-06-08:/mae297/petros-abraha.html</guid></item><item><title>Structural Coloration of Metallic Surfaces Using Elliptical Vibration Texturing</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/ping-guo.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Micro-structured surfaces are assuming an ever-increasing role since they
define the ultimate performance of many industrial components and products.
Surface micro-structures, when carefully designed, can alter the optical,
biological, tribological, and thermal properties of the original surfaces. The
bottleneck of applying this new technology to commercial products is
manufacturing efficiency. This talk demonstrates one example of using a novel
vibration-assisted machining method for fast creation of periodic
micro/nano-gratings for structural coloration. When the tool vibration is
coupled with a constant cutting velocity, periodic cusps can be generated due
to the machining marks. The periodic vibration-induced ripples can be precisely …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-06-01:/mae297/ping-guo.html</guid></item><item><title>Open Engineering</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/devin-berg.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As engineering researchers and scholars, we hope to have an impact on the world
through our work. Many of us went into this field in pursuit of the dream of
using our skills and training to help improve the lives of others.
Unfortunately, through the pressures of career advancement we find ourselves
creating and publishing work that will be read by a handful (sometimes fewer)
of others. While practicing open engineering won't guarantee that more people
will read your work, it does remove many of the barriers to access that make it
difficult for millions of people around the world …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-25:/mae297/devin-berg.html</guid></item><item><title>Musculoskeletal Loss and Exercise Countermeasures for Space Flight</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/alan-hargens.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During spaceflight astronauts experience musculoskeletal losses and moderate to
severe lumbar pain. There is also a significant incidence of herniated
intervertebral disc (IVD) in astronauts, especially in the first year after
return to Earth. The pathogenesis of back pain during and after spaceflight is
currently unknown. Our current investigation aims to understand this higher
incidence of herniated IVDs and back pain. Studies incorporate pre- and
post-flight imaging, functional tests, and pain questionnaires of International
Space Station (ISS) crew members to ascertain mechanisms of back pain as well
as degeneration and injury to spinal structures. Presently six out of 12 ISS …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-18:/mae297/alan-hargens.html</guid></item><item><title>OpenSim: A simulator to study human-device interaction</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/jennifer-hicks.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the interactions between robotic systems and the human's complex
musculoskeletal system is a key bottleneck in designing effective assistive
devices. OpenSim is free and open source software for modeling neural and
musculoskeletal structures and predicting and analyzing movement. We are using
the software to predict the effects of assistive devices on human performance
in tasks such as load carriage, running, and jumping.  We have discovered that
passive assistive devices have the potential to markedly increase jump
performance. These results were generated using a dynamic optimization that
simultaneously optimized human performance and device design. We have also used
simulations to …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-11:/mae297/jennifer-hicks.html</guid></item><item><title>Lessons Learned: A Left-Handed Lifetime of Inventing</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/dick-bourne.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Dick Bourne, founder of the Davis Energy Group, the UC Davis Western Cooling
Efficiency Center, and Integrated Comfort, Inc. will review key experiences in
his life as an inventor, for two purposes: 1) the drawing of lessons useful to
the young and creative; and 2) entertainment. From his inventive start as a
grad student in the Stanford Design Division, where he was also a writer in the
Engineering Case Program, Dick will describe how studying the inventing process
and working with creative designers nurtured his early (but failed) attempt to
support a family as an independent inventor. After reviewing several …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-04:/mae297/dick-bourne.html</guid></item><item><title>Systematic Understanding and Modeling of Origami Sheet Metal folding for Enhanced Mechanical Properties and Topological Re-configurability</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/ala-qattawi.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging fabrication process for mechanical structures can offer advantages in
terms of reduced energy requirements or increased design flexibility. However,
the body of knowledge lacks the design consideration of such components to
optimize the final part's characteristics. Researchers have established best
practices and design considerations for traditional manufacturing processes to
reduce the product cycle and increase the efficiency and quality of final
components. This talk will discuss the implementation of design-for
manufacturing approach for Origami sheet metal (OSM) folding fabrication
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSM folded structures are promising topological entities that can be folded
from a flat metal sheet to complex 3-dimensional …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-27:/mae297/ala-qattawi.html</guid></item><item><title>Modeling and Simulation of Advanced Reactors and Fuel Cycles - Computational Science and Engineering</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/kathryn-huff.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Nuclear power provides the majority of our nation's safe, reliable, carbon free
energy. Advanced nuclear reactors and nuclear fuel cycles promise to further
improve passive safety, fuel utilization, and environmental impacts of this key
energy source. This seminar will discuss open, reproducible, computational
approaches to modeling and simulation of the multiple coupled physics and
scales inherent to these systems. Approaches will include (1) agent based
modeling of future energy growth, reprocessing, and fuel management scenarios,
(2) the interplay between probabilistic and deterministic neutron transport
methods for design and safety analysis, and (3) development of reactor physics
kernels for the MOOSE …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-20:/mae297/kathryn-huff.html</guid></item><item><title>Wheelchair Fabrication in Developing Countries</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/ralf-hotchkiss.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ralf Hotchkiss will track the design of the Whirlwind Wheelchair from its
beginning thirty years ago to the present and on into the future. From the
first design breakthroughs of barefoot blacksmiths to the high tech testing and
manufacturing methods of today, surprise breakthroughs in basic wheelchair
design have come from the backyard inventors of some forty developing
countries. These inventors form the Whirlwind Network of wheelchair riders and
designers. Their goal is not only to make wheelchairs available in the poorest
of countries; it is to radically improve the durability and rough-ground
mobility so that wheelchair riders can live …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-13:/mae297/ralf-hotchkiss.html</guid></item><item><title>High Power Handling Hot-Switching RF-MEMS Switches</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/xiaoguang-liu.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Due to its low insertion loss, high isolation, high linearity, wide bandwidth,
and near-zero dc power consumption, radio frequency micro-electromechanical
(RF-MEMS) switches have been an emerging technology with significant potential
in many high frequency circuits and systems, especially those requiring
reconfiguration. In this talk, we present several RF-MEMS switch designs that
can significantly extend the hot-switching life-time of RF-MEMS contact
switches. To prevent the contact degradation during hot-switching events,
series and/or protection contacts are added in parallel with the &amp;quot;real&amp;quot;
contacts. For unpackaged devices using Au-Au as the &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; contact material and
Pt-Au as the protection contact material, we …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-06:/mae297/xiaoguang-liu.html</guid></item></channel></rss>