<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>MAE 297</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/</link><description>Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering Seminar</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>TBA - Surface Treatment of Materials</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/tba-surface-treatment-of-materials.html</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-06-08:mae297/tba-surface-treatment-of-materials.html</guid></item><item><title>TBA - Manufacturing</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/tba-manufacturing.html</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-06-01:mae297/tba-manufacturing.html</guid></item><item><title>Open Engineering</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/open-engineering.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As engineering researchers and scholars, we hope to have an impact on the world through our work. Many of us went into this field in pursuit of the dream of using our skills and training to help improve the lives of others. Unfortunately, through the pressures of career advancement we find ourselves creating and publishing work that will be read by a handful (sometimes fewer) of others. While practicing open engineering won't guarantee that more people will read your work, it does remove many of the barriers to access that make it difficult for millions of people around the world to obtain and engage with the engineering knowledge that is so often locked away behind the paywalls employed by some of the biggest academic publishers. With the availability of modern tools, it is easier than ever to make available not only the final, polished product of the engineering research or design process, but also the data, code, solid models, or any other artifacts produced along the way. By making the full scope of our work available, we have the opportunity to see our work replicated, expanded upon, or even driven in new directions we hadn't conceived. Through these mechanisms, the impact of our work is magnified. To realize these benefits, it may be necessary to re-examine the reward structures which drive our career advancement and in some cases, restructure the role of the publicly funded research institution in society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bio"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Berg is an Associate Professor and Program Director of the Mechanical Engineering program at the University of Wisconsin-Stout. He is passionate about finding ways in which we can broaden the impact of engineering design and development and make the products of engineering scholarship as openly accessible as possible. In pursuit of these goals he founded &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tjoe.org/"&gt;The Journal of Open Engineering&lt;/a&gt;, an experiment in fully open engineering publishing, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.engrxiv.org/"&gt;engrXiv&lt;/a&gt;, an eprint server for the engineering field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-25:mae297/open-engineering.html</guid></item><item><title>Musculoskeletal Loss and Exercise Countermeasures for Space Flight</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/musculoskeletal-loss-and-exercise-countermeasures-for-space-flight.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During spaceflight astronauts experience musculoskeletal losses and moderate to
severe lumbar pain. There is also a significant incidence of herniated
intervertebral disc (IVD) in astronauts, especially in the first year after
return to Earth. The pathogenesis of back pain during and after spaceflight is
currently unknown. Our current investigation aims to understand this higher
incidence of herniated IVDs and back pain. Studies incorporate pre- and
post-flight imaging, functional tests, and pain questionnaires of International
Space Station (ISS) crew members to ascertain mechanisms of back pain as well
as degeneration and injury to spinal structures. Presently six out of 12 ISS
crew members have completed all pre- and post-flight testing. Preliminary
results to date document: 1) decreased functional back-muscle extensor test
(Biering-Sørensen test time), 2) decreased cervical and lumbar muscle
functional cross-sectional areas with partial recovery by R+45 (only 21% in
neck), 3) increased spine stiffness in flexion, 4) increased spine
straightening, 5) decreased quality of vertebral bodies (anterior wedging and
endplate irregularities), 6) variable water content changes and 7) no
significant changes to disc height and lumbar length. Our results for
morphological, biochemical, metabolic, and fluoroscopic kinematics of the spine
may aid development of countermeasures to reduce back pain and decrease the
incidence of herniated IVDs post-flight. Countermeasures proposed in-flight
should include integrated cardiovascular and musculoskeletal exercises to
reproduce normal, daily Earth-like stresses. Our long-term objectives are to:
1) promote crew health and well-being inflight, 2) optimize post-flight
rehabilitation and translate our findings for Earth Benefit. Supported by NASA
grants NNX10AM18G and NNX13AM89G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bio"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hargens is Professor and Director of the Orthopaedic Clinical Physiology
Lab at the UCSD. He previously served as Chief of the Space Physiology Branch
and Space Station Project Scientist at NASA Ames RC and as Consulting Professor
of Human Biology at Stanford Univ. He teaches orthopaedic residents,
medical/graduate/undergraduate students at UCSD. His recent research concerns
gravity effects on the cardiovascular and musculoskeletal systems of humans and
animals. One of his students spent 6 months on the ISS, grew and ate vegetables
in space, while another flew on the Shuttle five times and was the first
astronaut to climb to the top of Mt Everest. Dr. Hargens also investigates
exercise devices to maintain astronaut health and performance in space. This
research is translated to help post-surgical treatment and rehabilitation of
orthopaedic patients, and to improve performance of athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-18:mae297/musculoskeletal-loss-and-exercise-countermeasures-for-space-flight.html</guid></item><item><title>OpenSim: A simulator to study human-device interaction</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/opensim-a-simulator-to-study-human-device-interaction.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the interactions between robotic systems and the human's complex
musculoskeletal system is a key bottleneck in designing effective assistive
devices. OpenSim is free and open source software for modeling neural and
musculoskeletal structures and predicting and analyzing movement. We are using
the software to predict the effects of assistive devices on human performance
in tasks such as load carriage, running, and jumping.  We have discovered that
passive assistive devices have the potential to markedly increase jump
performance. These results were generated using a dynamic optimization that
simultaneously optimized human performance and device design. We have also used
simulations to develop a set of design principles for using assistive devices
to reduce the metabolic cost of running and walking with a heavy load. OpenSim
is more than a software package—it has also become a diverse and vibrant
community of researchers, teachers, and clinicians who use the software for a
wide range of applications from improving treatment for children with cerebral
palsy to designing exercises to prevent bone and muscle loss during
spaceflight. This talk will provide an introduction to the OpenSim project and
highlight several research applications where we are using the software to
study human-device interaction and aid assistive device design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="biography"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hicks is a Senior Research Engineer in the Bioengineering Department at
Stanford University. She serves as the Associate Director of the National
Center for Simulation in Rehabilitation Research and the Director of Data
Science for the Mobilize Center. Her research uses biomechanical modeling,
along with machine learning methods, to predict the effects of surgery,
devices, and other interventions on human movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-11:mae297/opensim-a-simulator-to-study-human-device-interaction.html</guid></item><item><title>TBA - HVAC, Companies, Patents, Inventions</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/tba-hvac-companies-patents-inventions.html</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-05-04:mae297/tba-hvac-companies-patents-inventions.html</guid></item><item><title>Systematic Understanding and Modeling of Origami Sheet Metal folding for Enhanced Mechanical Properties and Topological Re-configurability</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/systematic-understanding-and-modeling-of-origami-sheet-metal-folding-for-enhanced-mechanical-properties-and-topological-re-configurability.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging fabrication process for mechanical structures can offer advantages in
terms of reduced energy requirements or increased design flexibility. However,
the body of knowledge lacks the design consideration of such components to
optimize the final part's characteristics. Researchers have established best
practices and design considerations for traditional manufacturing processes to
reduce the product cycle and increase the efficiency and quality of final
components. This talk will discuss the implementation of design-for
manufacturing approach for Origami sheet metal (OSM) folding fabrication
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSM folded structures are promising topological entities that can be folded
from a flat metal sheet to complex 3-dimensional geometrically constrained
structures. It can offer a reduced demand on the manufacturing and design
resources such as energy, heavy machinery, and complex die design. In addition,
the OSM structures can exploit materials with high strength-to-weight ratios
such as aluminum and stainless steel. Despite its potential, there is a lack in
the understanding of the parameters affecting the topological
re-configurability and load bearing capabilities for full scale OSM structures.
Specifically, the folding performance through the thickness of metal materials
with focus on failure mechanism along the fold lines. The technique of
combining folding structures and metal materials poses challenges that require
further investigation. This talk discusses the extension of the Origami
technique to the fold forming of sheet metal products represented in modeling
approach and design considerations for the topological variations, the
geometrical validity, and mechanical performance analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="biography"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ala Qattawi is an assistant professor of Mechanical Engineering at University
of California, Merced. She received a PhD in Automotive Engineering from
Clemson University, SC, in 2012 and became the first women in the United States
to earn a PhD degree in Automotive Engineering. Her research interests include
design for manufacturing, sustainable manufacturing, and Origami  sheet metal
folding as well as applications to the vehicle’s body in white design and
structure. Qattawi received the Hellman Faculty Award in 2016 and was named an
Emerging Scholar of the Year 2017 by the Diverse: Issues In Higher Education
Emerging Scholar. Qattawi's research has been funded by the University of
California President Office, The Hellman Foundation, and The University of
California Institute for Mexico and the United States (UC MEXUS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-27:mae297/systematic-understanding-and-modeling-of-origami-sheet-metal-folding-for-enhanced-mechanical-properties-and-topological-re-configurability.html</guid></item><item><title>Modeling and Simulation of Advanced Reactors and Fuel Cycles - Computational Science and Engineering</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/modeling-and-simulation-of-advanced-reactors-and-fuel-cycles-computational-science-and-engineering.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Nuclear power provides the majority of our nation's safe, reliable, carbon free
energy. Advanced nuclear reactors and nuclear fuel cycles promise to further
improve passive safety, fuel utilization, and environmental impacts of this key
energy source. This seminar will discuss open, reproducible, computational
approaches to modeling and simulation of the multiple coupled physics and
scales inherent to these systems. Approaches will include (1) agent based
modeling of future energy growth, reprocessing, and fuel management scenarios,
(2) the interplay between probabilistic and deterministic neutron transport
methods for design and safety analysis, and (3) development of reactor physics
kernels for the MOOSE (multiphysics object oriented simulation environment)
framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="biography"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kathryn D. Huff is currently an Assistant Professor in the Department of
Nuclear, Plasma, and Radiological Engineering at the University of Illinois at
Urbana-Champaign where she leads the Advanced Reactors and Fuel Cycles Research
Group (arfc.npre.illinois.edu). She holds an affiliate faculty position with
the National Center for Supercomputing Applications and is one of the
University of Illinois' most recent Blue Waters Professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was previously a Postdoctoral Fellow with both the Nuclear Science and
Security Consortium and the Berkeley Institute for Data Science at the
University of California - Berkeley. She received her PhD in Nuclear
Engineering from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in August 2013 and her
undergraduate degree in Physics from the University of Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her current research focuses on modeling and simulation of advanced nuclear
reactors and fuel cycles. She is currently the elected chair of the Fuel Cycle
and Waste Management Division of the American Nuclear Society. Through
leadership within the Hacker Within, Software Carpentry, SciPy, the Journal of
Open Source Software, and other initiatives she strives to advocate for best
practices in open, reproducible scientific computing.  With colleagues,
collaborators, and friends, she has co-authored two books to help scientists
with these practices: Effective Computation in Physics, O'Reilly, 2015 and The
Practice of Reproducible Research, UC Press, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-20:mae297/modeling-and-simulation-of-advanced-reactors-and-fuel-cycles-computational-science-and-engineering.html</guid></item><item><title>TBA - Appropriate Technology</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/tba-appropriate-technology.html</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-13:mae297/tba-appropriate-technology.html</guid></item><item><title>High Power Handling Hot-Switching RF-MEMS Switches</title><link>https://moorepants.github.io/mae297/high-power-handling-hot-switching-rf-mems-switches.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Due to its low insertion loss, high isolation, high linearity, wide bandwidth,
and near-zero dc power consumption, radio frequency micro-electromechanical
(RF-MEMS) switches have been an emerging technology with significant potential
in many high frequency circuits and systems, especially those requiring
reconfiguration. In this talk, we present several RF-MEMS switch designs that
can significantly extend the hot-switching life-time of RF-MEMS contact
switches. To prevent the contact degradation during hot-switching events,
series and/or protection contacts are added in parallel with the &amp;quot;real&amp;quot;
contacts. For unpackaged devices using Au-Au as the &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; contact material and
Pt-Au as the protection contact material, we have demonstrated unprecedented
hot-switching performance of 150-million actuation cycles at 1-W  and
50-million at 2 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="biography"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Xiaoguang &amp;quot;Leo&amp;quot; Liu received his B.S. degree from Zhejiang University,
China in 2004 and his Ph.D. degree from Purdue University in 2010. He is
currently an assistant professor in the Department of Electrical and Computer
Engineering at the University of California, Davis. His research interests
include radio frequency microelectromechanical (RF-MEMS) devices and other
reconfigurable high frequency components, high frequency integrated circuits,
and biomedical and industrial applications of high frequency communication and
sensing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2017-04-06:mae297/high-power-handling-hot-switching-rf-mems-switches.html</guid></item></channel></rss>